Shall I tell my son that
he should have a dream?
(Questioner) When the other person
asked about dreams,
you said that it is not necessary
to have a dream.
If you have one, that's fine.
But it is better not to have one.
I have always told my son to have a dream,
to figure out what he wants,
and to follow his dream.
These days there are many
lectures on this subject.
I would like to hear your thoughts on them
and about what you said earlier.
There are two meanings for the word dream.
One is to mean something hollow
and futile.
People say, "Don’t be in your dreams!",
that means something is not real.
The other means a wish.
Someone has a wish.
These are two meanings of the word.
Chasing after a dream
comes with high risk of futility,
if you really have a wish for something.
Life brings pain.
You really want to do something,
but the situation won't allow it.
Then you feel unhappy, right?
In that situation, you have to give it up.
But it is not wrong to have nothing
in particular you want to do.
What does it mean to have
nothing in particular you want to do?
Put another way,
you will be happy to do anything.
Since you can do anything,
you have many more choices in life.
Why do we have to do something
or become something?
If there is a dream to pursue,
you can do that.
If not, you can do whatever else.
Long time ago, did the farmers farm because
that's what they really wanted to do?
Did they feel as if they
had to do that or die?
The kids are stressed because you keep
feeding them with these futile ideas.
That's why you ask these questions.
"I don't know what my dream is"
"I don't know what I like"
"How do I figure it out?"
They keep asking these questions endlessly.
The older generation planted
the futile ideas.
The parents should not tell them
such things out of their own ambition.
Instead of the parents telling
the child to find his dream,
they may advise,
" you might try to live this way."
You may suggest,
" My dream was to become a scientist,
but I didn't. How about you succeeding
my dream and becoming a scientist?"
If he says OK,
he will carry on with your wish.
If he says no, you cannot force it on him
even though he is your child.
That's how far you take it.
But you vaguely say,
"Have a dream. Have a dream."
What sort of dream?
What if he comes up with an absurd dream?
Someone asked me earlier
after reading some book.
The book said that if you teach
the child right starting in 6th grade,
he can be accepted
at Seoul National University.
So you torment him, trying to get him
accepted at Seoul National University.
This is how you ruin a person.
All such books must be burned.
Let the children be children.
They can study if they want to.
Play if they want to.
Naturally, the children like to
play more than study.
Even so, you can guide them
to study in between playing times.
Kids are being kids when they play.
But kids are made to study
by force against their will.
So, the studying is not fun.
Studying is not done out of curiosity.
Because they are forced to study.
When I was growing up, kids were forced
to work so it was really hard.
Even in elementary school,
when we came home from school,
we were not able to study.
We were told to cut the grass,
feed the cows, and get the fire woods.
Some kids ran away from home
because the work was too hard.
Then the parents would go
searching for their kids.
These days, the study load forced on the
kids are heavier than the fire woods.
It could kill these kids.
This is why kids commit suicide or run
away from home these days. Or they rebel.
So, don't make them
carry such heavy burden.
If they don't study,
have a talk with them.
Not studying does not cause
others harm, do they?
No, it doesn't. It's not included
in the four precepts I mentioned before.
Falling grade does not
harm anybody, right?
No, it doesn't.
In fact, it is a good deed because
it will raise another student's grade.
No need to scold your children for this.
You need to communicate with them.
Because it concerns their lives.
So, ask,
"Aren't you planning to go to college?"
"No, I won't" he may say.
I personally, don't think
it's necessary to go to college.
I didn't even finish high school,
but I am doing quite well.
So just tell him to do
what he wants to do.
If he says yes,
tell him that certain steps
are necessary in Korean college system,
so if he wants to go to college,
he must study.
This is the law of cause and effect.
He may understand this and study.
If he still doesn't study,
say, "What a relief!
You are releasing me from the
financial burden. You're a good boy. "
Just praise him rather like this.
You have to want to study
for studying to be effective.
You can't study effectively when forced.
What we need in the future is creativity.
Only self-motivated studying
brings out creativity.
Thank you. (Applause)
(Sunim) Pass the mic.
Pass the mic to the student.
(Sunim) Give the mic to her son.
Take the mic and tell me any complaints
you have about your mom.
Be honest. What's the complaint?
Nothing? No complaints?
(Student) No, I don't have any.
(Sunim) Isn't studying hard?
No,
Are you a good student?
Just...
So so. Do you want to study?
It's no fun?
Don't know?
No.
(Sunim) You don't know
if you want to study or not?
You like playing games or studying?
(Audience Laughter)
What grade are you in?
7th grade.
You don't know if you like game playing
or studying as a 7th grader?
Haven’t you played games? Have you?
(Audience Laughter)
(Sunim) Okay.
You can be considered a good boy.
(Sunim) Or you're overly conscious of
your mother. (Audience Laughter)
(Sunim) Don't mind your mom.
Just tell me.
(Sunim) Can't do it.
(Audience Laughter)
(Sunim) You're worried about what will happen
when you get home. (Audience Laughter)(Sunim Laughter)
(Sunim) Okay, okay. Take his mic.
(Sunim Laughter)
It's nice when kids listen to
their parents, right?
But after the teenage years,
it is better that they don't listen.
Not listening to their parents means that
they have their own opinions, no?
That is how they become independent.
When they are young,
doing as they are told is good.
But it's not so good later.
It is not so good if they listen to
the parents after they turn 20.
Kids who listen to their parents
after 20, can't turn out well.
Why? If Buddha listened to his parents,
would he have become Buddha?
No he couldn't.
(Sunim Laughter)(Audience Laughter)
If Great An Joong Gun had told
his parents before leaving home that
he was going to fight for
our country's independence,
would they have told him to go ahead?
Kids shouldn't listen to their parents.
When the kids are grown,
they can take their parents advice,
but they have to make their own decisions.
Why isn't it always good
to listen to the parents?
Parents always focus on what's safe
when it comes to their children.
But, you can't only do
what's safe in life.
Safety is important, but, at times
you need challenges, take risks, and fail.
You grow through these experiences.
But, the parents won't allow their children
these trial and errors, and failures.
Thus, the children can't mature.
Young children need their parents
to take care of them,
but when it comes to reaching true maturity,
the parents are the biggest hindrance.
So if you really love your children,
take really good care of them
when they are young.
But, as they get older,
you have to let go of them.
And you have to respect them.
If your child asks you something,
you need to take a step back
so he can figure it out himself.
You teach them attentively
when they are young.
As they get older,
you should not teach them.
If he asks, pretend not to know
and say, "I don't really know".
"You are the student.
How would I know?"
"Go ask the monk.
You go figure it out"
You have to take a step back like that.
So they can do it on their own.
If your daughter brings home a boyfriend
and asks what you think, say,
"I don't know.
He is your boyfriend, not mine.
I am sure you know him better than me".
"I am always okay with whoever
you choose because I trust you."
Encourage her like that,
but don't meddle.
If she still asks, "What do you think?
Come on, do you think he is okay?"
you can't keep saying
you don't know, right?
Then you can say,
"I am not good at judging men.
If I were, you think I would have
married your father?"
(Audience Laughter) (Sunim Laughter)
You can make excuses
like this and step back.
Don't keep meddling.
So, they can make their
own decision for their lives.
Then, they will not become burden to you.
Care for them till they're 20, then they
can live on their own afterwards.
Otherwise, even after they're 30 or 40,
they will remain as heavy burden on you.
After they reach 20, the children
need to live as adults.
Instead, they are still dependent
on parents as if they're still nursing.
This is why the world is so complicated.
You heard of the Kangaroo family, right?
That means the parents are
doing something wrong.
It's a problem of raising kids as if
they are pets rather than people.